<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pages on Cuterwrite's Blog</title><link>https://cuterwrite.top/en/page/</link><description>Recent content in Pages on Cuterwrite's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>cuterwrite</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cuterwrite.top/en/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>关于 | About</title><link>https://cuterwrite.top/en/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cuterwrite.top/en/about/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://cuterwrite-1302252842.file.myqcloud.com/blog/GA11qGVXwAASzAL-2023-12-25.webp" alt="Featured image of post 关于 | About" />
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="https://cdn.bootcdn.net/ajax/libs/aplayer/1.10.1/APlayer.min.css">
&lt;script src="https://cdn.bootcdn.net/ajax/libs/aplayer/1.10.1/APlayer.min.js" defer>&lt;/script>
&lt;script src="https://cdn.bootcdn.net/ajax/libs/meting/2.0.1/Meting.min.js" defer>&lt;/script>
&lt;meting-js
server="netease"
type="song"
id="441102548"
autoplay="true" loop="true">
&lt;/meting-js>
&lt;p>👀 Welcome to my personal blog! I am cuterwrite, a PhD student passionate about exploring the fields of computer science and technology. Here, I will share my insights, learned technologies, and research-related content with everyone. I hope my blog can bring you inspiration and joy!&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>About me: I am currently pursuing a PhD in Computer Science. My research focuses on communication optimization in high-performance computing (HPC) and large-scale spiking neural network simulations. I am dedicated to utilizing high-performance computing technology to enhance the efficiency of spiking neural network simulations and exploring the possibilities of brain-like computing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Research Interests:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>High-performance computing: I have a strong interest in parallel computing, distributed systems, and high-performance computing architectures. I hope to provide better solutions for solving complex computational problems through the study of these technologies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Spiking Neural Networks and Brain Simulation: Spiking neural networks are a computational model that simulates biological neural networks, offering higher energy efficiency and computational capability. I focus on how to optimize the communication and computation processes of such networks to enhance their performance. Brain simulation is a method of using computer technology to simulate the structure and function of the brain, aiming to deeply understand the working principles of the brain and provide new research directions for the fields of artificial intelligence and neuroscience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Communication Optimization: In large-scale parallel computing, communication overhead often becomes a performance bottleneck. I am committed to researching methods to reduce communication latency and improve communication efficiency in order to achieve better performance in high-performance computing scenarios.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Blog Content: In this blog, I will primarily share technical articles related to my research areas such as high-performance computing, communication optimization, and brain simulation. Additionally, I will occasionally share some interesting or thought-provoking technical articles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cover: 2023/12/8, ONE OK ROCK Asian tour Hong Kong. I love ONE OK ROCK very much! 🙌&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I hope my blog can bring you inspiration and joy!&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://skillicons.dev/icons?perline=20&amp;amp;i=github,gitlab,git,stackoverflow,vscode,idea,js,html,css,c,nodejs,python,java,vue,spring,maven,mongo,redis,mysql,md,linux,bash,docker,kubernetes,nginx,jenkins,tensorflow,pytorch,golang,flutter,cs,cpp,cmake,d3,dart,discord,bots,dotnet,githubactions,gradle,graphql,kafka,latex,php,postman" width="auto" loading="lazy">
&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>归档 | Archives</title><link>https://cuterwrite.top/en/archives/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cuterwrite.top/en/archives/</guid><description/></item><item><title>搜索 | Search</title><link>https://cuterwrite.top/en/search/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cuterwrite.top/en/search/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>